[Music]
[Applause]
blood flow restriction training for
glutes
take one so blood flow restriction
training or bfr it's also called katsu
training has been very popular for the
last decade and i remember being
skeptical just like everyone else but
there is so much research supporting bfr
training once upon a time i had a
research review
with my colleague chris beardsley and we
were reviewing 50 articles per month but
i was going through
around 100 sports science journals every
single month checking out all the
articles that were published and month
after month i would find evidence
supporting
blood flow restriction training now i
followed this science along the way
but i always assumed it was just for
muscles distal to the cuff
you know if you wrap here then it would
be good for your biceps and triceps and
maybe forearms or you or if you wrapped
your upper legs it would be good for
your quads and hammies and maybe the
calves
you're occluding the blood flow to those
muscles and therefore they're going to
fatigue faster but then i began
to stumble across research supporting
blood flow restriction training for
muscles that were that were not distal
to the cuff you know there were uh torso
muscles you know the chest
and the glutes and i thought well how
could this be well my first assumption
was to think
well it must be something systemic you
know when you
when you use bfr you're doing things
that maybe alters the hormonal mulu
maybe this increases signals that
ultimately end up
increasing muscle protein synthesis all
over the body and then it occurred to me
well maybe you're fatiguing
the synergists and so you know in the
case of the glutes
maybe you're doing squats and you
fatigue the quads so fast that then the
glutes have to do more work
same thing if you fatigue the hamstrings
then the glutes would have to do more
work there too
assuming the movement was hip extension
you know the research on pre-exhaustion
showed that when you do like flies or
pec deck before you do bench press
pec activation during the bench press
actually goes down what goes up
is your front delt and tricep activation
so there's another plausible
explanation through by which blood flow
restriction training would work
there's in fact a review paper published
by huang and willoughby
in jscr from 2017 and they speculate to
what the mechanisms of blood flow
restriction could be
with regards to hypertrophy okay you've
got secreted hormonal responses
like testosterone igf-1 and growth
hormone you've got
translation initiation by intracellular
signaling responses
like mtor and p70 s6k you've got
metabolite accumulations like lactate
you've got fiber type recruitment
patterns you have satellite cell
activity
and finally you have muscle cellular
swelling so
the first possible mechanism that's easy
to understand that's just saying when
you do
bfr training you ramp up your production
of testosterone and growth hormone igf-1
the second proposed mechanism is more
confusing and that has to do with the
intracellular signaling responses
the third metabolite accumulations
that's the burn you know the burn that
you feel that
metabolic stress that you get okay the
next one the fiber type recruitment
patterns here you end up fatiguing
so much faster so you're going to
recruit way more motor units
to compensate for the fatigue satellite
cell activity this is like
muscle stem cells that lay outside the
muscle cell
and when called upon they will actually
lend their nuclei
into the muscle and you end up with more
nuclei
therefore you have more messengers to
call upon the cell to increase protein
synthesis
and finally cell swelling that's the
pump
and that may work by producing outward
pressure onto the cell
and then the cell perceives it as a
threat and ramps up
protein synthesis so there you have six
potential mechanisms so here's the deal
all of these mechanisms are the same
mechanisms through by which heavy
resistance training works so it's like
yes
when you perform blood flow restriction
training it works it's going to build
muscle but what if you're already
lifting heavy weights is it going to do
anything that heavy weight training
won't
that's the question we need to answer
but that alone wouldn't mean that blood
flow restriction training is invaluable
you know there's a lot we don't know and
the one main positive
of bfr training is that you can use
light loads
and get good results you know imagine
taking something that you can do for
around 30 reps
you know and you get 30 reps and then
you rest like 30 seconds you do 15 more
then you rest another 30 seconds you do
15 more and you're done
well the joints aren't going to get
nearly as beat up and if that packs a
powerful punch
then that can prolong your training
career so there are two scenarios where
this would be valuable
number one is whenever something's beat
up something's not feeling good your
shoulder some
something's not feeling your muscle you
can still do bfr
and use lighter loads maybe preserve the
muscle there while that nagging issue
heals up and the other is for healthy
people maybe we should be alternating
maybe we train certain muscles heavy
and other muscles lighter with bfr and
then we flip-flop
so you could have some sort of
periodized schedule where you're taking
advantage of the hypertrophy stimulus
issued by bfr training while unloading
certain joints and structures
while you focus on others i hope that
made sense so let's get back to how
blood flow restriction training might
help other muscles grow
if i occlude my quads and hammies how
are my glutes going to grow
well one study showed that bfr training
with the leg muscles
led to greater results with the upper
body muscles as long as you did light
training for the upper body if you did
no training for the upper body
there were no improvements but if you
did light training for the upper body it
showed
better results another study involved
restricting the arm muscles
while doing bench press twice a day with
30 percent of one rep max
which is very very light but doing
around four sets of 15 to 20 reps
and the chest muscles grew in the blood
flow restriction group but in the group
that didn't restrict their arms the
chest didn't grow
so bfr caused the chest muscles to grow
larger another study looked at walking
and squatting with blood flow
restriction training obviously with the
legs restricted
now the walking group did not grow their
glutes but the squatting group
did and they only used 20 percent of one
rep max which is very light but they did
it twice a day for two weeks
now here's another review paper by abbey
and colleagues and i just want to read
you the conclusion they said low
intensity of 20 to 30 percent of one or
max
resistance exercise training combined
with bfr elicits muscle hypertrophy
in both blood flow restricted limb and
non blood flow restricted muscles then
they go on to say
muscle activation is an important factor
for bfr training induced muscle
hypertrophy and the minimum exercise
intensity for muscle hypertrophy may be
around
10 percent of mvic for the blood flow
restricted limb muscles
and about 20 percent of mvic for
non-restricted trunk muscles so that's
crazy
10 to 20 percent of maximum is nothing
but it does appear that
for the trunk muscles in order for them
to grow you need a little bit heavier
stimulus than for the
restricted muscles downstream here's
another study
looking at blood flow restriction
training with walking and the glutes did
not grow as well
so just walking with cuffs on won't help
the glutes grow
another study had subjects for two weeks
do leg extensions with twenty percent of
one rep max and
leg press with thirty percent of one arm
two days per week for 12 weeks
now the group that didn't restrict their
blood flow their glutes didn't grow but
the group that did
grew their glutes it wasn't to some
great degree it was only four point four
percent but the leg press isn't the best
glute exercise so
so there's another study supporting bfr
for glute training now another study
used kind of a similar design
the subjects trained twice a week for 12
weeks but they did band squats and band
leg extensions
kind of weird and the glutes didn't grow
even in the bfr group
now another study had subjects squat and
leg curl
twice a day for two weeks one group wore
cuffs the other group didn't and the
group that wore cuffs grew their glutes
to a much larger extent than the group
that didn't
9.1 versus negative 0.6 percent for the
non-restricted group
and the loads in that study was only
twenty percent of one ram
so again light loads helped grow the
glutes so that sums up the research on
bfr and glute training and as you can
see there are no studies looking at
heavy resistance training for the glutes
versus heavy training
and bfr or heavy training for the glutes
versus bfr
so if you're the type of lifter that
doesn't like to lift you hate lifting
you just want to use light loads and not
train that hard
bfr would absolutely work for you
especially in the restricted muscles but
maybe even in the non-restricted muscles
too like the trunk muscles but most
people watching this video are serious
lifters and right now there's not much
evidence to suggest that
bfr training would be additive to a
pre-existing
high-quality glute training program for
example what i outlined in my rule of
thirds video
like if you're doing a training program
from brett contreras would it be even
better to add in bfr training
i don't know i personally don't think so
but i'm open-minded so
in addition to not having much research
to go by we don't even know what
exercise they'd work best with
and the reason why we can't even
speculate about that is because we don't
even know
how it works as i mentioned earlier the
main theory is that it just fatigues the
muscle so it drives up muscle activation
to compensate for the fatigue so say you
have cuffs up here
and you're doing curls because you have
restricted blood flow to the arms you're
going to get high levels of muscle
activation
sooner than if they weren't occluded now
maybe if you're doing a compound
movement
like say a chin up you know maybe your
your biceps would fatigue faster so your
lats would end up working harder and
that's one way how the glutes might
benefit because say you're doing squats
or lunges
and the quads fatigue so fast then the
glutes end up having to do more but i'm
skeptical about that so let's break this
down from a practical perspective
all right if that's the way it works
then yes squats and lunges would work
back extensions would be a good exercise
too because your hamstrings would
fatigue faster now the glutes have to do
more
what about abduction the quads and
hamstrings aren't synergists for
abduction
so theoretically wearing the cuffs
wouldn't help you grow bigger glutes by
wearing the cuffs
you know what about glute bridges and
hip thrusts yes you'll feel the quads
and hamstrings working hard when you're
going super heavy but bfr
is used pretty much exclusively with
lighter loads so would it matter would
would fatigue in the quads and hammies
in a hip thrust lead to greater glute
activation and would the glutes have to
compensate for the fatigue
leg muscles i don't think so but
anecdotally my clients who have worn the
cuffs
do feel like they get a much greater
pump even when it's with things like hip
thrust and abduction
they think they get a greater pump in
the glutes but that's just
subjective feedback that's not very
scientific we're not measuring the pump
through
ultrasound or something like that but i
think one of the main mechanisms
through by which bfr could be valuable
for glute training
is psychological in nature and you guys
are going to laugh and think this is
stupid but
there is so much research on the placebo
effect on the effect of like
self-confidence and things like
self-confidence can actually affect your
results
so you might be wondering what the heck
is he talking about all right there used
to be this wrestler back in the day
named the ultimate warrior now this guy
was absolutely crazy but as you can see
in the picture
he always tied off his arm muscles and
it made him look pretty badass
his arms would be so pumped so i noticed
when women
wear those bfr cuffs it makes their butt
stick out more
it kind of perks the glutes up it makes
them rounder makes them stick out more i
think it would make women feel more
confident
you know they'd be strutting their stuff
walking tall
they'd be happy to be in the gym because
they'd glance at themselves in the
mirror and they'd be like wow i look
good
it's the same as when i wear the cuffs
and my muscles get so pumped
like my biceps and triceps or my quads
and hammies i like the way i look
so that could be a third mechanism
through by which it works all up in
there
so i'd like to leave you with some
practical recommendations but again we
don't have much to go by
i personally don't think that they're
gonna help much if you're already doing
booty by brett for example
every base is already covered every
mechanism is already covered when you
train
under a system like booty by brat but it
can't hurt to try
bfr is very safe and it's especially
wise to try this if you've got some
nagging joint or
say you have knee pain or something and
you want to train around it
then go light for super high reps and
then the knee would heal quicker
and it would prevent atrophy it would be
logical to think oh i should wear it
during my warm-ups because my warm-ups
are light loads anyway you know during
my glute activation why not wear the
cuffs
but then you run the risk of fatiguing
yourself for the big lifts your heavy
compound movements which you should be
using
progressive overload with so it could
decrease your results
in that fashion by preventing you from
setting prs on your big lifts
so maybe instead you do burnouts at the
end of the workout after you've gotten
all the big rocks out of the way
you went for prs you hit a big lift like
squats or hip thrusts or lunges or
romanian deadlifts you got those out of
the way and now you put the bfr cuffs on
and maybe you do a high rep circuit of
body weight movements hell maybe even
combine the glute lube with it now the
exercises that make the most sense would
be squat and lunge type movements
hinging movements as for bridging and
thrusting movements and abduction
movements
i don't know i don't think it can harm
you it's just that in time when we learn
the mechanisms better we might come to
find that it only works with certain
exercises and not others
specifically exercises that utilize the
quads or the hammies which therefore
cause the glutes to do more now
luckily i have my client breann
alexander here to demonstrate all of
these exercises here in
glute lab las vegas and i had her roll
through a bunch of different types of
exercises
and by the way she got a huge pump with
them
yeah here's bree's butt after doing
around 10 minutes
of bfr training as you can see it looks
pretty pumped up
and the cuffs are making it appear even
larger you know she loved them
so it's important to know that when you
do bfr training
it's not going to work as well with
heavy heavy weights you know you don't
want to be doing
you know 315 pound hip thrusts unless
you're my client carly who can bust that
out for 30 reps
the most popular protocol involves
taking 30
of one rep max busting out for like 30
reps and then doing two sets of 15 reps
following that with only like 30 seconds
to a minute rest but you can experiment
that's just the one they use the most in
the research
main things stick to high reps body
weight light dumbbell light loading
bands
those are work great with bfr training
again i would not use bfr training with
your heavy compounds
i'd slap the cuffs on towards the end of
the workout and do a burnout
do some circuit training do some glute
circuits so i hope you like this
scientific analysis
the company's selling the bfr bands they
quote stuff on bfr training but it's for
other muscles they'll quote studies
looking at quad hypertrophy which makes
more sense because it's occluded in my
opinion the company's selling these bans
they tend to over hype bfr training
obviously because they're trying to make
a profit but they don't seem to
understand the science that well they're
marketers not scientists
it's important to re-emphasize here we
don't have anything to go by really
we've got clues
so i picture the manufacturer one of
these products reaching out to some
nerdy scientists in a lab
paying them off to say something like
you know these are gonna do this and
this and this
and they kind of use research on other
muscles to overhype bfr glute training
and he's full of crap because he doesn't
know if that really works on the glutes
that way you know i also picture some
big meathead bodybuilders saying
you want big glutes just squat or just
do this and
ignore all that stupid crap and he's
wrong as well
nobody knows right now we don't have
enough evidence it's all conjecture at
this point and i think i'm in the best
position to make the conjecture because
i've spent my life in a gym
and i got my phd and know how to
interpret the evidence so it's anyone's
best guess now so
in conclusion i don't know of many
bodybuilders who use these cuffs
that's not to say that it still isn't
useful those bodybuilders might be
missing out but
i surmise that it's not going to be
beneficial when you're already lifting
heavy
and going for prs but if you like these
bands or they make you want to exercise
more or go to the gym
because you love the way they make your
butt look have at it but slap them on
after the heavy compounds have been done
make sure to do high reps with short
rest periods with them and stick to
exercises where you're gonna fatigue the
synergists
all right please hit like please give it
a thumbs up make sure you're following
me
i got a lot more to come in 2021 thank
you for watching
if you like what you saw in this video
and you want to train under my system
and principles
then i invite you to click on the link
below and subscribe to booty by brett
and join the thousands of other happy
members who are seeing amazing results
[Music]
yes